Guide to the Margaret Jordan Sprinkle and Henry Sprinkle Papers, 1935-1986
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Margaret Jordan Sprinkle and Henry Sprinkle papers 1935-1986
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Sprinkle family.
2.5 Linear Feet 150 Items
Dr. Henry Call Sprinkle was a Methodist Minister from Mocksville, North Carolina, and graduate of Duke University and Yale University. Henry married Margaret Louise Jordan in 1930. The Sprinkle family spent the majority of their lives travelling the world for missionary work.
The collection contains diaries and notebooks detailing the travels of Dr. Henry Call Sprinkle and his wife, Margaret Jordan Sprinkle. Main subjects are family life in North Carolina, Duke University events, European politics, WWII, and missionary travel throughout Europe, South and Central America, the Caribbean, Africa, Asia, and Australia. Materials range in date from 1935 through 1986.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Also, all or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. Consequently, there may be a 24-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Margaret Jordan Sprinkle and Henry Sprinkle Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2013.
Biographical and Historical Note
Henry Call Sprinkle, born November 20, 1902, in Mocksville, NC, was the son of Henry Clay Sprinkle and Annie Van Eaton Call of Mocksville, NC. Margaret Louise Jordan was born on January 20, 1903. Henry attended Trinity College (now Duke University) and obtained an A.B. in 1923 and an A.M. in 1924. That same year, Henry joined the North Carolina Conference and was assigned as a junior preacher and director of religious education at First Methodist Church, located in Rocky Mount, NC. He earned a B.D. in 1927 and Ph.D. in Philosophy, 1929, both from Yale University. On February 17, 1930, Henry Sprinkle married Margaret Jordan. Dr. Sprinkle pursued post-graduate studies in 1935-36 and spent a year at Cambridge University in London, England. From 1929 to 1942, Dr. Sprinkle continued to serve a number of churches throughout North Carolina. He went on to serve as a Navy Chaplain in the US Navy during WWII, and held the rank Lt. Commander. Dr. Sprinkle also served as assistant editor of the Adult Student in Nashville (1930-1935), editor of the North Carolina Christian Advocate (1945-1949), Associate Editor of World Outlook (1949-1952), Editor of World Outlook (1952-1966). The Sprinkles retired from ministry work and settled in Mocksville, NC in 1967. In 1981, Mocksville United Methodist Church established The Sprinkle Preaching Mission in honor of Henry and Margaret Sprinkle, recognizing the many contributions they made to Mocksville and Davie counties. Dr. Henry Call Sprinkle died on May 7, 1989. Margaret Louise Jordan Sprinkle died in December, 1996.
Collection Overview
The collection includes the travel diaries and notebooks of Margaret Jordan Sprinkle and Henry Call Sprinkle, written from 1935 to 1986. This collection is arranged into two series: Margaret J. Sprinkle Diaries and Henry C. Sprinkle Diaries and Notebooks. Early diaries and notebooks contain detailed information about their travels in Europe, providing commentary on the differences between American society and various other places, particularly English society, culture, attitudes and perspectives. Margaret's entries provide significant insight relating to political climate of Europe at the time and events leading up to WWII. Starting in the 1950s, the diaries reflect the broader international travels of the Sprinkles, as a result of their involvement in missionary work. Entries usually include travel itineraries, as well as descriptions of various social, cultural, and political conditions of various cities and regions throughout Europe, Africa, Asia, South and Central America, and Australia. The majority of diary entries detail daily activities, family life, social obligations, events in North Carolina, particularly in Durham, and events at Duke University.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Sprinkle, Margaret Jordan
Sprinkle, Henry
Sprinkle family
Travel -- Diaries
Women missionaries
United Methodist Church (U.S.)--Missionaries
World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American
Duke University -- History
Soviet Union -- Description and travel
Africa -- Description and travel
Europe -- Description and travel
Related Material
Margaret Jordan Sprinkle was the sister of Charles E. Jordan and B. Everett Jordan, whose papers are also held at the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
Contents of Collection
- Margaret Jordan Sprinkle Diaries, 1935-1986, (5 boxes)
  - Collection information, biographical file, genealogy (Box 1)
  - Diaries, 1935-1936, (4 volumes) (Box 1)
    Box 1 contains the original diaries, as well as digitized, bound copies, detailing Henry and Margaret Sprinkle's year abroad (1935-1936) at Cambridge University in England. While living in London, the Sprinkles travelled extensively throughout Europe, visiting France, Belgium, Holland, Northern Ireland, Scotland, Norway, Sweden, Denmark, Finland, USSR Russia, Poland, Czechoslovakia, Austria, Switzerland, and Germany. Margaret Sprinkle frequently wrote about their travels in Europe, providing commentary on the differences between American society and various other places, particularly English society, culture, attitudes and perspectives. Throughout the diaries, Margaret's entries provide significant insight relating to political climate of Europe at the time and events leading up to WWII. Many entries mention Soviet Russia; various labor strikes in France and Belgium; the election of a socialist president in France; Adolph Hitler; Benito Mussolini in Abyssinia; Haile Selassie's visit to England; and a number of other observations on international politics.
  - Loose papers, articles, and photographs, 1935-1936 (Box 1)
    Folder includes Margaret Sprinkle's writings and reflections on Soviet Russia, miscellaneous clippings on the Moscow Power Institute, a Vogue magazine article from 1941 on Belgium's Great Cathedral, as well as cards, postcards, and photographs.
  - Diaries, 1941-1959, (13 volumes) (Box 2)
    Box contains yearly diaries, with dates ranging from 1941 to 1959. Entries from 1948-1952 are contained in one diary and there are no diaries for 1945 or 1955. This box also contains miscellaneous inserts from the 1944, 1948, and 1958 diaries.
    These diaries include details of Margaret's personal and professional life, including lists and descriptions of daily activities such as meetings, appointments, visits, and special events throughout North Carolina, especially related to Duke University. Margaret's diaries also include travel itineraries, documenting her domestic and international travels with her husband. Among the countries visited by the Sprinkles beginning in the late 1940s throughout the 1950s were, England, France, Holland, Switzerland, Mexico, Guatemala, Costa Rica, Panama, Peru, Bolivia, Chile, Argentina, Uruguay, Brazil, Haiti, Dominican Republic, Puerto Rico, Cuba, Wake Island, Japan, Hong Kong, Saigon, Singapore, Thailand, Burma, India, Ceylon, Yemen, Egypt, Lebanon, Syria, Jordan, Jerusalem, Greece, Italy, Spain, and Portugal. Also included are entries about Henry during his service in the US Navy during WWII, Franklin D. Roosevelt, and D-Day. Three ballot books are among the inserts from 1948. These ballot books also serve as a travel diary noting a family trip to Europe in 1948, with Henry and Henry II.
  - Diaries, 1960-1969, (14 volumes) (Box 3)
    Box contains yearly diaries, with dates ranging from 1960 to 1969. The following years have multiple volumes: 1964 (2 volumes), 1967 (2 volumes), and 1968 (3 volumes). This box also contains miscellaneous inserts from the following diaries: 1962, both volumes for 1964, 1965, 1966, the 1967 Day Book, one of the 1968 diaries, and the 1969 diary.
    The entries within these diaries provide details of Margaret’s personal and professional life, including lists and descriptions of daily activities such as meetings, appointments, visits, and special events throughout North Carolina, especially related to Duke University. Margaret’s diaries also include travel itineraries, documenting her domestic and international travels with her husband, particularly detailing their mission trip to Africa. Countries visited by the Sprinkles during the 1960s include the Netherlands, Germany, Austria, Liechtenstein, Switzerland, Italy, Monte Carlo, France, Luxembourg, Denmark, Sweden, Norway, Holland, England, Belgium, Spain, Ghana, Ivory Coast, Liberia, Nigeria, South Africa, Congo, North Rhodesia, Zimbabwe, Rhodesia, Mozambique, Kenya, Ethiopia, Sudan, Greece, Italy, France, Mexico, Italy, Greece, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Switzerland, Yugoslavia, Moravia, Japan, Hong Kong, Philippines, Australia, Brazil, El Salvador, Morocco, Portugal, and Bermuda.
  - Diaries, 1970-1979, (11 volumes) (Box 4)
    Box contains yearly diaries, dates ranging from 1970-1979. Diary entries for 1973 span 2 volumes. This box also include miscellaneous inserts from the 1972, 1973, 1977, and 1978 diaries.
    Diaries include entries related to Margaret’s personal and professional life, including lists and descriptions of daily activities such as meetings, appointments, visits, and special events throughout North Carolina, especially related to Duke University. Many entries, as well as some inserts and loose materials, include information on the purchase and renovation expenses of a house located in Pinellas County, Florida. The Sprinkles continued their international travels throughout the 1970s, visiting such countries as Holland, France, England, Ireland, Scotland, Wales, Iran, China, South Korea, Taiwan, Thailand, Malaysia, Singapore, Hong Kong. This box also include miscellaneous inserts from the 1972, 1973, 1977, and 1978 diaries relating to Pinellas County, FL; Methodism in America; and loose travel notes.
  - Diaries, 1980-1986, (9 volumes) (Box 5)
    Box contains yearly diaries, dates ranging 1980-1986, as well as a travel journal, listing the various trips taken by Margaret and Henry Sprinkle from 1960-1982. This box also contains loose papers from 1980s.
    These diaries include details of Margaret’s personal and professional life, including lists and descriptions of daily activities such as meetings, appointments, visits, and special events. Unlike the previous decades of diaries, documentation throughout the 1980s is sparse. Of particular interest is a travel journal, listing the various trips taken by Margaret and Henry Sprinkle from 1960-1982. During the early 1980s, the travel journal notes that the Sprinkles traveled to Bermuda, China, Japan, Hong Kong, and the islands of Britain. This box also contains loose papers from the 1980s relating to Duke Alumni holiday activities; travel and cultural information about Hong Kong, China, and Japan; and the Sprinkle Preaching Mission.
- Henry C. Sprinkle Diaries and Notebooks, 1935-1984, (1 box)
  - Diaries and Notebooks, 1935-1984, (25 volumes) (Box 5)
    Box contains diaries, notebooks, notepads, and address and date books, ranging from 1935-1984, as well as undated materials. There are no notebooks, diaries, or other materials from 1936 to 1960. This series is also missing entries from 1962-63, 1965-1968, 1970-1971, and 1977. This box also contains miscellaneous inserts and letters from the 1935 notebook, and a guidebook to Historic Savannah, including miscellaneous Savannah pamphlets.
    Henry recorded his notes and thoughts on philosophy, ethics, and religion within these notebooks and diaries. Many of the notebooks also feature a schedule of personal and professional activities, as well as various adresses and contact information. Of particular note within this series are letters of recommendation from Yale and Henry's request to study abroad at University of Cambridge.